[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE Radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. Today I'm talking
to Ashley Peacock. He's the author of
Serverless Apps on Cloudflare and he was
a previous guest talking about
diagramming and software engineering.
Ashley, welcome back to Software
Engineering Radio. Hey, glad to be back
and looking forward to talking about
Cloudflare today. For anybody in our
audience who hasn't heard of Cloudflare,
what is it? So, I guess Cloudflare has
been around for quite a while. It
started out as a kind of cloud security
company and then over the years they've
had different phases where they
gradually grow from doing security
related to websites, so B protection,
content delivery network, things like
that. and they've slowly migrated to
also introduce a developer platform
that's not unlike a so you can go on you
can deploy your apps you know they've
got everything you need and those are
the kind of two main pillars I would say
of what Cloudflare offers and I think
maybe a lot of people's first exposure
to Cloudflare is as a CDN so maybe you
could explain at a high level what a CDN
is yeah so let's say you have a
WordPress blog and you host it on a
virtual machine or some shared hosting,
you know, you're effectively hosting it
on a a single server. And let's say
you're really lucky, you write a really
positive blog post, it goes, you know,
viral, gets, you know, retweeted
everywhere. Your little VM or your
shared hosting might not survive the
rush of traffic. And what a CDN can do
is it distributes your content from your
blog. So the images, the JavaScript,
CSS, and the content itself globally
around the world. And then what happens
is whenever a request comes in, the CDM
will check and see if it has content in
its cache. If it does, it will return it
without ever hitting your VM. So that
gives you decreased latency, so fast
responses for end users. And it also
puts a lot less pressure on your VM. And
then with CloudFare, they'll also give
you some security protection to protect
you from, you know, attacks and, you
know, bot protection and things like
that. So it's effectively like a proxy
sitting kind of like in front of your
website as a bit of a shield and just
gives you those benefits that I that I
outlined. And you mentioned it's
starting to become more of a developer
platform. What do you mean specifically
by that? So if you go back to the
origins of Cloudflare, it was a security
company. you know the CDN we talked
about that's how it largely started and
the very kind of beginnings of its
developer platform were allowing people
who used the proxy to do things like
modify the request headers before the
content is sent back. So you could add a
HTTP header for example or modify the
response and that was the very kind of
beginning of what's called a Cloudflow
worker which is like a serverless
function. You can write some code, be
executed when a request comes in and
then over the years they've taken what
was something very simple to just modify
the headers and you can now deploy
fullyfledged applications to cloudless
develop platform. So workers give you
compute very similar to AWS Lambda in
some ways but also very different and
they have the other kind of core
building blocks that you would expect to
build applications. So databases,
caches, cues, all those sorts of things
that you, you know, you use from ads
like R2 and Aurora and all those things.
But it's a lot more focused than AWS. So
ads these days has I don't know how many
services it has, but it's in the it's in
the hundreds, right? And Cloudflare
focused on the kind of core building
blocks for your website, I would say.
And particularly in the last few years,
they've really kind of pushed that
develop platform and added what I would
say are the kind of missing pieces. It's
like they didn't have a database, they
didn't have object storage, but it's
really come on leaps and bounds in in
recent years. And I think it's at the
point where it's starting, you can start
to see the momentum and people starting
to pick it up and realize actually it's
a kind of complete platform for building
apps these days. And you mentioned
workers as an example. It sounds like
that's very similar to AWS's Lambda. Why
would someone who for example is already
on AWS look at something like workers? I
think one of the huge selling points for
Cloudflare in my opinion is with Lambda
for example, let's just take Lambda
because it's probably the biggest one
that everyone knows. It's been added to
AWS, but they also have hundreds of
other services. They've kind of bolted
on serverless and Lambda onto their
offering and it works, you know, very
nicely. It's not a bad product by any
means, but with Cloudflare's offering,
they always envisioned their entire
platform being serless. So, it's
designed from the ground up to be
serverless. Not only that, but they
focused on things that are important to
me and you with developer experience and
how easy and enjoyable it is to build on
the platform. Like, if you've ever built
anything on iOS lately, you probably
spend half an hour trying to get your IM
policy just right cuz it keeps on not
quite working. You tweak it, you tweak
it, tweak it, eventually you get there
or you need it and then you need a VPC
or you need an IP address or or
something. With Clifford, there's no
such roadblocks. It's more like the
platform is kind of working with you and
they've really designed it for engineers
versus ads to a point has to kind of
build and market to the CTOs and people
that are not building those products,
right? Whereas Cloudflare I think has
taken a slightly different approach.
What it sounds like is maybe the
developer experience or the ease of use
is more optimized on Cloudflare than it
would be for someone getting started
with AWS. Yeah, I can give you a couple
examples. So I think things that you
don't get generally other places. So
let's say you want to connect your
worker, so your kind of serverless
function to a database or a cache or any
of the resources that Cloudflare gives
you, you use what's called a binding.
And if you've ever used dependency
injection, it's kind of like automated
dependency injection, but rather than
you doing it yourself at runtime when
your worker is started by Cloudflare cuz
they, you know, a request comes in, your
worker is invoked and spun up
automatically by Cloudflare, the request
is executed against it. And at that
point, they will inject the binding that
is needed to run your worker. So if you
have access to a database, it's just
injected for you and it's effectively in
the environment for you. You don't have
to mess around with secrets or any
configuration. It's just there for you.
And that also then flows in. And this is
kind of why I was talking about with the
integrated nature and the developer
experience of when you run your worker
locally, Cloudflare will use their kind
of local emulation to spin up
effectively kind of like stubs that are
faking. they're not running against real
resources. You can just run that locally
and you'll get the exact same experience
as you would in production, but you have
to make no changes. You can just run a
single command. It will start your
worker. It will have access to all your
bindings, however many there are, and it
all just pieces together very kind of
seamlessly. I'm trying to understand how
the binding works in practice. So with a
traditional application, if you had a
database, you would need let's say
credentials or a connection string and
like you said, you could put that into
some kind of secret store or environment
variables. How are the bindings
different? What does my code actually
look like where it can find how to
connect to the database in this case?
Yeah. So you first because everything is
serverless, you create the resource you
need and cloud have their own CLI called
Wrangler. So if you're just hacking
together something, you can easily just
run a command with Wrangler that will
make you a database or a cache or
whatever you need. It will basically
give you back an ID or sometimes you use
the name of the resource that only your
account has access to. And then you take
that ID or that name and you put in a
configuration file that's historically
been in toml but it's now you can now
use JSON and it's effectively just yeah
your configuration goes in a JSON file
and then at runtime Cloudflare reads
that file and it injects the correct one
and in that configuration file you have
things like environment so you can have
obviously you don't want to have your
staging and production databases to be
all mixed. So you can effectively spin
up multiple databases and can configure
the correct one for each environment and
then yeah when it's run at runtime it'll
be injected. So the distinction I I
guess is instead of having references to
a specific host name or IP you are
putting in this ID into your
configuration and then Cloudflare is
figuring out where that database or that
other service actually is. Yeah.
Correct. And then in your actual code,
there's a parameter on your or your
worker. If you're using a framework,
they'll have code that the framework has
written that makes it accessible, but
it's effectively like it being in your
environment for you, and you don't have
to worry about how you interface with it
necessarily because they will inject
like an SDK for you to use. Each of them
comes with an SDK. There are rappers
from the community that obviously
enhance them, but generally speaking,
all the kind of core functionality is
wrapped for you in an SDK that's
injected for you. at runtime. And you
had mentioned the local development
example. So it sounds like if you're
running locally in that config file,
there's something you could put that
tells it instead of trying to connect to
my production instance running on
Cloudflare instead run this local
emulator and connect to that instead.
Not even that. It will effectively when
you run the command by default it will
just run and emulate everything locally
and then if you want to run it remotely
you can actually run them remotely by
effectively just passing in a flag when
you run the command and then it will
effectively push your worker into like a
a sandbox environment. So it doesn't
deploy it to like your account. It's in
a kind of safe sandbox environment but
it has access to all your bindings. So
let's say I don't know you're finding it
difficult to debug an issue in let's
just say staging right cuz you know
staging you can mess around with the
data it's not user data you could easily
run that worker locally point at the
staging database and run everything
locally and then try and replicate
yourself super easily which I think is
super nice. So what this would look like
is you have your project with all your
source code files and you use the
command line tool that that Wrangler
tool and based on which flags you pass
in it either will emulate the
dependencies by default or like you said
you can pass in a flag and then it will
actually run it on a server instead.
Yeah, that's exactly right. I'm trying
to just make sure I understand the
binding part
specifically when you say things are
being injected at runtime like what
exactly is being injected like what do I
see in my code and then what is actually
going in at runtime. So each worker has
an entry point. So if we just take a
bare bones worker the function is called
fetch and it has a few parameters on it.
One of them is obviously the incoming
HTTP request. So you can pull out the
you know the URL the headers whatever
you you need and then the second one is
basically literally called environment
and on that environment when you're
configuring it in your wrangler file
alongside the ID you define a name for
the binding so you know you give it a
descriptive name for whatever it is if
it's a database or a cache or whatever
and then you basically do environment do
the name and then you can just call
methods on it. So let's take a cache.
Very simple, right? With a cache, you
basically you can set or you can get or
you can probably you can delete and
maybe list. You basically just call
those methods on the environment and it
will execute those remotely against
whatever the binding is for such as a
cache. in your configuration file, that
TOMOML file or that JSON file, that's
where you create these environments and
you specify what services or resources
you have available and then in your
environment parameter, you can access
all those things you put in your config
file. Yeah. And CloudFlare will just
effectively read that configuration file
and inject all of those at runtime
seamlessly. We talked a little bit about
workers which you said are similar to
lambdas. So those are serverless
functions. Since serverless is sort of
an overloaded term, can you sort of
explain to people who aren't familiar
with them what that really means to you?
Yes. So as you said there are many
definitions for serless. So if you ask
100 engineers they're going to give you
a different definition. I think for me
there are kind of some core tenants of
what makes serverless serverless. I
think one of the main ones is that you
pay based on usage. So there are some
services from AWS, I think Reddus is one
of them where it has like a base cost.
So even if you're not using it, you have
a base cost. So it's it's not scaling to
zero. And for serless it it should scale
to zero. You shouldn't need to do any
maintenance. So you shouldn't need to
like upgrade the version of the
programming language or the software
you're using or if you're using let's
just say kick with reddus you know you
shouldn't need to upgrade your reddit
version it should be handled for you by
the platform and you shouldn't need to
wait for your resources to spin up
because you're not spinning up a server
so the whole thing about serverless is
it should be quick and that's exactly
what it is with cloudflare you know if
you issue that wrangler command to
create a database you're kind of
creating a logical database rather than
an actual physical instance and that is
available instantly for you to use. So I
think those are some of the key things
of when it comes to service, what I
would consider it service to be. And
something I used to hear about often is
what people refer to as the cold start
problem where it takes time for the
resource to be available. Is that
something that you also have to be aware
of on Cloudflare? No. So there are
exceptions as with all things, but
unless you have a huge worker that is
perhaps doing something on boot, you
will generally never see cold starts
with Cloudflare. And the reason is the
runtime is very different to what you
can run on at least the typical Lambda.
Cloudflare's environment is is their own
runtime and it's based on the same
runtime that you run in Chrome. So it's
it's called the VA engine. It's exactly
what runs in your browser. So that makes
JavaScript kind of king at least.
JavaScript, TypeScript are the primary
languages that are supported. You can
also use web assembly to then compile
from pretty much you know any language
with good web assembly support. Rust is
a big one cuz Cloudflare internally use
a lot of Rust. And then that runtime is
also enriched with node libraries. So
it's not full node but it's got kind of
compatibility with a lot of node.
Especially recently they've been really
adding the kind of compatibility to it.
But in terms of the cold start, what
they do is quite clever where when a
request comes into your worker or really
if a request comes into anything in this
day and age, it's all goes through HTTPS
and it needs to do what's called a TLS
handshake where the client basically
they exchange certificates and they do a
handshake and it basically verifies that
the connection is secure and that takes
I don't know how long it takes but it
takes some milliseconds where in that
time Cloudflare basically knows where
the request is going and it's warmed up
your worker.
while it's doing that handshake. So the
time the handshake is finished, let's
say it takes 50 milliseconds, your
worker is then able to handle that
request instantly and there's basically
no cold start and that's thanks firstly
to what I just explained with the
handshake and secondly the runtime
because you can imagine you open a tab
each one of those is its own V8 runtime
and you can see how quickly your tab is
available right it's available instantly
so I think it's a mixture of their
technology stack plus some clever
engineering it sounds like so maybe
that's one of the trade-offs between the
cloudflare workers and lambda where I
believe with lambda they have specific
language support and it's not
specifically tied to can it run in web
assembly whereas with cloudflare it
sounds like if you can compile to web
assembly then you you can run it yeah I
would say the vast majority of code at
the moment is written in javascript and
typescript for sure because that's as
you can imagine it's basically like a
browser so it's it natively runs out of
the
There was Python introduced towards the
end of last year or earlier. Yeah, last
year which is natively running, but it's
not fully there yet. I think you can see
the direction they're going in, but
things like dependencies don't quite
work that well yet, but I think more
will come and certainly Rust is one of
the main ones cuz it has the web
assembly support. It's for sure a
trade-off where on AWS you can have a
full node environment for example or you
can have Ruby or whatever else that they
support on Lambda. And something I've
heard about web assembly is that there
are certain limitations where you can
use these languages but certain IO level
access for example is maybe not
available. Does that also apply on this
environment? It does. So whether you're
using web assembly or using JavaScript,
you actually don't have access to the
file system same as in the browser
because you have the same kind of
restrictions that you have in the
browser. So if you're reading
configuration files, you can't read
those from the file system because you
just simply don't have access, you need
to push them to object storage or if the
configuration is quite simple,
particularly in JavaScript, you can
obviously just define objects and have
the configuration defined in your code.
But yeah, the restrictions that you've
probably encountered probably apply here
as well, I would say. So, we've mostly
been talking about workers, but AWS, as
you mentioned, has hundreds, if not
thousands of different services. I
imagine Cloudflare doesn't have quite as
many, but there's still probably a lot.
What would you say are the core services
to focus on outside of just workers? So
you have R2 from Cloudflare which is
basically an S3 compatible object
storage. So if you want to store user
generated files or your own generated
files and have them served from a
bucket, it's completely compatible with
S3. You can even just port all your
content from S3 into R2 and use the AWS
SDK and everything will just mostly
work. There is a few kind of little APIs
that aren't implemented, but generally
speaking, it will work. And the nice
thing about Cloudflare is that it has no
egress fees unlike AWS. So if you're
doing a ton of egress via S3, you could
move that content to R2 and you're not
going to pay egress and it might save
you obviously a lot of money cuz the
egress costs are they're kind of like a
bit of a hidden cost, aren't they? Where
you're not really it's kind of hard to
work out where it's coming from
sometimes and they can really rack up
for a worker or R2. You don't get
charged egress. Besides R2, you have D1
which is their serverless database
that's effectively SQL light. They're a
little different to things you'll find
on AWS because they're designed to be
per tenant. So they're limited in their
kind of size if you will. It's not me
you're meant to have one database per
user. You have multiple databases
typically. They have a key value store.
So it's interface is similar to Reddius
but its kind of design is quite
different. It's designed for kind of
read heavy rather than write heavy and
it's eventually consistent rather than
reddis. So it's obviously just you know
it's realtime sub millisecond but it's
also you know reddus is is hosted in one
location it generally sits close to your
application server right whereas with
cloud for everything is global and I
guess like we were talking about
trade-offs earlier one trade-off is
because it's global in nature there are
these eventual consistencies concerns
where you write it'll take a while to
propagate around the the entire network
in terms of like hosting your static
content because until recently at least
workers were primarily just for handling
APIs and you could do content but it was
much more common to use a framework. So
you can imagine Nex.js, Astro Spelt, all
the popular JS frameworks are deployable
to Cloudflare and they have a product
called pages and that effectively is
just your full stack hosting where it
will serve your static assets and it
will also convert your Nex.js roots for
example if you're using Nex.js it will
convert those to kind of effectively
like a worker at build time. So it works
with Cloudflare's platform. So that
allows you to host your your front end
and more recently you can also host the
assets with workers too. Those are some
of the key ones I would say. And when
you mentioned how D1 is like SQLite but
it's really designed to I think you said
it's almost like having one database per
user. Is that because the size of the
database is limited and the IO in terms
of simultaneous rights and reads is
limited? What are the limitations or or
differences in design there? The
limitation I think is probably
exclusively the storage. So I think
they're limited to 10 gig which
obviously per user is probably generally
fine but if you have thousands 10
thousands hundred thousands of users
it's not going to scale to meet that
demand. So yeah it's definitely designed
in a way that it's split by tenant or
user or some sort of other
configuration. In terms of like what I
would use I would probably use an
external database for now because it
doesn't have things yet that it needs
like at the moment bindings are static.
So imagine you create 10 databases with
10 different IDs. It becomes really
difficult to bind those. So you could
add a binding for every single user, but
if you have 10,000 users, that's going
to be a lot of bindings. I don't think
they're going to let you even bind that
many things. And secondly, like I said,
everything is global. But with D1, the
database is created where you first make
the request or you can give it a
suggestion of where you want to be
created. So Europe or North America and
so forth. And I think this year read
replicas will drop then you'll have a
truly global database and there have
been murmurings of like dynamic bindings
which you would imagine would be
something useful for this but I think at
the moment a lot of people that are
using Cloudflare are using other
database providers cuz it's it's easy to
connect to Neon is a really popular like
Postgres serverless database. You can
connect it to any serverful Postgress
database such as Aurora and they have a
product called Hyperdrive. That's quite
cool because you can imagine if you're
in a serverless environment, those
functions are spun up and spun down all
the time. And if you have like a
connection string, it takes a while to
connect that database. It might take 500
milliseconds to connect to that
database. But with Hyperdrive, it
basically creates connection pools. So
Cloudflare will do it automatically for
you. So rather than each time it having
to connect to your postgress database
and handle the security and everything,
those connections are ready to go. So
that removes that problem and I think
it's a really nice solution to allow
people to use external databases with
Cloudflare. But like I said, most people
I think tend to use external ones for
now. And with that hyperdrive example,
would that be where you create a
database in for example in
AWS and in your TOML file or your config
file you are specifying your connection
string and all that stuff and you're
saying that I want hyperdrive to connect
to my database. Then at runtime your
application will know okay I'm
connecting to hyperdrive to do this and
not directly to the database. Yeah
exactly. So it basically works out the
box. So you don't need to change
anything like obviously apart from
configuring hyperdrive but it will yeah
it will run the connection pools for you
and with a little bit of configuration.
You can use all the SDKs you would
normally use cuz it's just pulling and
effectively proxying the requests. So
yeah from what I've heard at least it's
out of the box. You just plug it in and
it'll work. And with the key value
example, you mentioned that it's like
Reddus, but it's more for read heavy
workloads. What's the limitation on
rights? Is it just it can only accept a
certain amount per second? In terms of
rights, you can write unlimited times
per day once you're on the paid plan
that's just $5 a month. And in that pay
plan, you do get a lot. And you can
write to the same key once every second.
But the issue is more it takes 60
seconds for that right to propagate. You
can imagine you're using Reddits, right?
You you've often write read, write,
read, write, read. But that's just not
going to work. And if you have users
around the world, so like if I make a
request to a worker, for example, we
haven't touched on it, but that worker
is spun up as close to the end user as
possible. So if I make a request, I'm
I'm in London, it's going to spin up
that worker in the London data center,
and then wherever you are in the US,
it's going to spin up a worker in the US
close to you. And the latency will be
much quicker than if you're hosting it
in an AWS region where we both have to
go to different places. Maybe, you know,
I have to go to America or you have to
come to Europe. It's higher latency. But
what you have then is when data is
written, let's say to KV, if your worker
is in the US, it's going to write to KV
in the US and then it's going to have to
propagate around the whole network. So
if I then 1 second later go and access
or read from the exact same key, I might
get the old value, not the new value. So
it just makes it a little bit difficult
to support like highr workloads. It's
it's designed really as like a heavy
heavy cache where you were infrequently
writing I think is is what it's designed
for and I think it was one of the first
kind of products alongside workers
because I think people were doing things
like orth at the edge where you know you
can write someone's JWT or whatever into
the cache and then it's just in there
and you just that's something where if
someone's like you know firing through
pages or page after page after page you
probably want to cache that content and
that's really heavy rewrite because you
log in once you write the token jobs are
that 60 seconds for propagation. When
you perform the write and let's say that
you use the off example, somebody gets
their JWT, it's written to the key value
store that's close to the user. I'm
assuming that should be reflected pretty
quickly. the 60 seconds you're talking
about is more that if that cache is read
from another country for example, maybe
that read replica, I guess you could say
that may not have the update for up to a
minute later. Yeah, that's exactly
correct. And that's primarily because
there is effectively like tiers within
the cache. So within a country you might
have multiple different data centers and
each one of those will have their own
kind of cache and then you might have a
regional kind of central data center
where it's like the next tier up and
then you have kind of very central the
kind of really big data centers that are
like the central stores. That means the
worker is going to write when the rights
happen they need to go to that central
store right so they're also a little
longer latency because it has to go to
one of those central stores and then
from there yeah it propagates across the
entire network. Yeah, I can see that
being a little bit tricky for you as a
developer where you have to account for
the fact that anything you do write if
it's the same user who wrote it reading
it back, you have a much higher chance
of it being updated sooner. But there's
since you said it's eventually
consistent, there's no guarantee that it
will. Yeah, that's exactly right. So
it's just one of those considerations
you have to have when you're using it
that that's if you went in and you
sometimes you see people like you know
they're expecting Reddus and it's not
Reddus and if you don't read the docs
and understand then that's going to be
it's going to be a bit of a shock when
you write and you're building something
and you send to your friend and they're
like oh something's broken like it's not
getting any data or something and it
yeah just it might take you a while to
work out unless you you understood. Does
that also apply to D1 the SQLite
equivalent as well? No. So at the moment
when you create a database that database
exists in a single location. So all your
rights are going to that one database if
you like. So this year I think they will
introduce read replicas and I don't know
how long the lats would be. They haven't
really kind of said but I suspect it'll
be a lot lower cuz you can imagine for a
database that's designed to be more
transactional you can't have 60 seconds
for a write to propagate. So my
assumption would be that the latency is
going to be a lot lower and even with
postgres or whatever right there is some
latency with the read replicas. So I
assume they factor that in and it'll be
I don't want to say it's going to be cuz
I haven't seen but I'm hoping it's going
to be what you'd expect when you have a
database with re replicas and that sort
of latency. That's pretty typical. So,
at least for the moment, since there
aren't the read replicas, you should be
able to treat D1 as if when you make a
write, it actually went to disk if you
were using SQLite as an equivalent.
Yeah, for sure. And there's definitely
use cases for D1. I think if you know
your data is not going to be huge or
let's just say you're processing some
asynchronous workloads, the the data is
very temporary. Maybe you write it and
then you delete it. you know, maybe
you've got some messages flying around
because I think we didn't we didn't talk
about it earlier, but CloudFare has a a
Q's product where it's effectively
sending a message into queue and then
you can have consumers pull from that
queue. So maybe you have some sort of
transient load where you can push that
data into D1 or if you just know your
data is not going to be huge. It's
perfectly fine. So I think there are use
cases for it. I think what I would say
is if you are going to use D1 because we
talked about the database is central and
the workers can be spun up anywhere in
the world across 330 cities that cloud
lays in and they have a clever little
tool or configuration called smart
placement and what that effectively does
is and this doesn't work just with D1 it
works with anything. So let's say you sp
up something in a worker and you have
something hosted in AWS database or even
just hitting like an EC2 image or even
just hitting like an API from a SAS like
from your on your back end maybe like
open API or whatever it might be. What
smart placement does is it it learns
over time as requests come in what
you're hitting downstream and it you
know records the latency and over a
period of let's say 24 hours it learns
your traffic patterns and what you're
hitting and it'll basically move your
worker and spin them up in the most
sensible place to reduce the latency.
And that's because you're then moving
the worker away from the user perhaps.
So they might have a slightly higher
latency to get to the worker. But if
that worker is then making five calls to
the database or three calls to some APIs
that are all hosted in, let's say,
America and your workers in, you know,
the person's in Europe, putting that
worker closer to those downstream
services is going to reduce the latency
because it's it's talking a lot more to
those services. So I think that's a
really nice thing that you can use and
there's no harm in enabling that and
it's completely free to use alongside
workers. So there's no downside to using
smart placement. And that smart
placement, would that apply to all your
users? Basically, like if I have users
in Europe and users in the US, you were
talking about how smart placement may
move the workers closer to where the
data is stored versus where the user is
stored. Is that sort of applied globally
where regardless of where I'm connecting
in the world, Smart Placement may
decide, oh, I should put this worker in
Virginia because that's where the data
stores it's connecting to are. Yeah,
it'll effectively just monitor all the
traffic going to your worker, which
obviously I guess it depends on your
your app, but is likely to be from
multiple places and then it will work
out after it's learned and obviously it
might adjust over time. So your app
changes, right? So it's not static. So
if you remove some API calls or
whatever, it's going to learn but yet it
will adjust for global. And you
mentioned how there's R2 which is very
similar to S3. Are there any large
differences between the two that people
should be aware of? I don't think
there's any huge differences. I think if
you use some of the more niche S3 kind
of features, then there is a page with
compatibility on that you can look up to
see what's not implemented. They are
definitely like quite niche things like
pre-signed URLs for example, you can do
those with R2 and it provides I want to
say the exact same kind of resiliency
and uptime guarantees that S3 has which
I think is something stupid like 11 9 or
9. I don't know how many nines it is but
it's a lot of nines. And I think R2
provides or at least claims to provide
the same uptime that S3 gives you. So I
think probably for 99% of usage or maybe
98% who knows but very high percentage
is going to be you could lift and shift
and it's probably going to work out of
our two rather than S3 and then you just
you save on the ingress and if you did
want to move there are some tools from
Cloudflare to help you move. They kind
of have funny names but one of them is
called Sippy and it's effectively like
an inflight migration. when something is
requested from the R2 bucket, if it's
not in the R2 bucket, it will pull it
from S3 at that point in time and then
all future requests will come from the
R2 bucket. And they have one called
Super Slurpa, which effectively is just
like a mass migration tool. So, it'll
pull all of your data out of S3, put it
in R2 in one big kind of batch. So there
are some useful migration patterns to
help you move um if you want to move
because I think one of the challenges
that Cloudflare has is obviously AWS has
quite a moat and one of the trickiest
things right of moving an app if you
wanted to move is the data right it's
not normally the apps that are hard to
move it's the data so I think having
those tools at least for two to help you
migrate is definitely useful you
mentioned there's a Q product as well is
that something you see a lot of people
using or is that more niche or early. I
don't know how widely it's used. I don't
think it's niche cuz it's obviously if
you can offload something asynchronous,
right? It's kind of nice to do. And I
think if you didn't have a Q's product,
there'd be some kind of raised eyebrows
of how do I do anything asynchronous
that you just can't. I think that's a
no-go. I think what's interesting is in
beta at the moment there's a product
called workflows and a really kind of
popular thing that's been around lately
is durable execution. So if you think
AWS step functions or I think it's
temporal IO and effectively what it is
is you lay out a list of steps that you
need to complete a workflow. I don't
know if this is univers but generally
speaking they will recover from outages
without losing where they are in the
workflow. So if imagine you have 10
steps and it gets to step five and you
need to call the downstream API, if the
API call fails just because they have a
momentarily blip, it will effectively
retry the workflow, but it won't rerun
steps one through four. It will jump
straight back to five and it will
basically store the data in cache if you
have transient data and pull it out
automatically for you and run through
that workflow. And I think it's really
becoming popular because of things like
AI and agents. And you can imagine these
kind of longunning processes that act as
workflows. Like if you want an AI agent
to write a blog post, right? You need I
saw someone building one. It's like
hundreds of prompts and hundreds of
requests. And if one of those just
fails, you don't want to reprompt a 100
failed requests. And it's going to be a
bit of a nightmare. So I think the
interesting thing is that that workflow
products, I think, is getting a lot of
usage even though it's only in beta. And
I can see it taking a kind of quite a
market share from Q's, but it's also
it's not really designed in a you think
about a queue, it's more kind of
transactional in that you're having
interervice communication with cues
versus workflows. It's kind of just
safely offloading and being able to
recover from failures and that kind of
thing. But yeah, those two are
definitely quite interesting. Yeah, I
think one of the reasons I asked about
the Q is I think anytime you have
something where you're running things
like the functions as a service, you
often need to have a lot of different
services talk to one another. You need
some kind of queuing system and it feels
like that has to be pretty robust and
that has to be able to be done in a way
that's like not super complicated or
super confusing. And so I'm trying to
get a sense of either with your own
projects or projects you've seen from
other people. Are they using Cloudflare
mostly for let's say the CDN aspect and
the serverless functions aspect but not
necessarily to chain a whole bunch of
things together and and build some kind
of more complicated workflow. Yeah, I
would definitely say the CDN aspect is
their bread and butter cuz that's what
they start out with. Huge huge
enterprises like the biggest companies
in the world are using Cloudflare for
their CDN. So, it's definitely the most
premier product they have, but I think
their dev platform is at the point where
it is starting to get traction and gain
some market share. Like if you look at
the Stack Overflow, what's it called?
the developer survey they do each year.
You can kind of see the Cloudflare is is
slowly moving up. If you go back 5
years, it just didn't have the maturity
around the products to realistically
challenge AWS in terms of deploying your
applications to into Cloudflare. I think
in terms of cues, I don't think I can
speak to like how often it's used. I
don't think I have a good read. I have
used it myself and it works very nicely
out of the box and I think it definitely
is easy to use. It's just writing a
message to a queue and then you
basically have a worker that is
basically acts as a consumer and it's as
simple as defining a function on your
worker. And like the fetch function is
what is used for HTTP requests. And then
you just define a separate fetch
function that I can't remember what it's
called but it basically is it's there
and whenever a message is received your
worker is spun up and it will consume
those messages and Cloudflare will
handle things like scaling the
consumers. So I can't remember the
limits but it will scale your work
horizontally based on demand which I
think is a really nice feature out of
the box. You don't have to worry about
things like CFKA and like partitions and
all that kind of, you know, fun stuff.
You don't have to worry about any of
that. And when we talked about local
dev, if you want to test this locally,
again, you don't have to go and find a
Docker container for CFKA and spin that
up and then connect everything together.
you can just test it locally and run
those two workers or run them in the
same worker however you want to do it
and you'll be able to see your messages
go into a queue and then be consumed
locally which I think is a really nice
kind of devx thing that we were talking
about and you were talking about I think
interervice communication right being in
a microservices architecture for example
you have lots of services talking to
each other and when we talked about
bindings earlier we didn't really talk
about service bindings which are how
different workers communicate and And
there are different flavors. The kind of
like older version that is still very
much used is you can define a binding
between two workers. Then those workers
can communicate with each other. And in
terms of your code, you call fetch,
which in JavaScript is just basically
making a HTTP request. And it looks like
it's making a HTTP request, but under
the hood, it's not really. It's using
Cloudflare kind of internal networking
magic to basically run the two workers
probably basically side by side. And
there's no actual networking. So it's
super quick, it's super reliable, and
you don't have the typical fallacies of
cloud computing that you often, you
know, hear touted about. You know, the
network's not reliable, bandwidth's not
limited, so forth. They're obviously
still concerns, but they're not as such
a big concern because you're not going
over the internet, right? You don't have
the HTB networking. And more recently,
to make it even more interesting is they
introduced the ability to do RPC. So you
can again connect two workers together
but rather than using the fetch method
where you have to like serialize and des
serialize JSON on both sides you can
actually just effectively call methods
on between two workers and as long as
what you're passing is serializable in
JSON so objects strings numbers etc. It
looks like you're making a local method
call but it's actually calling your
worker that's completely deployed
separate and then it obviously returns
you something that is serializable. So
it might return you an object. It can
even return you like functions that you
can then call. It really is quite cool.
Yeah. So it sounds like for the
serviceto service communication whether
it's the fetch replacement or the direct
RPC or the queuing system there are the
building blocks for somebody who who
wants to have these more complex
scenarios. Yeah, absolutely. And I think
it just makes it easier I think like
having these I don't know if you've come
across these kind of things before when
I tend to speak to people they're like
oh that sounds like you know they
haven't heard about these kind of things
before cuz I think those service
bindings and obviously RPC is not new
right but it the way that it just is
kind of built into the platform you
don't have to do anything right you
don't have to configure the RPC or
anything you just say connect this
worker to this worker in some
configuration and cloudfl handles the
rest so I think it's very powerful and
something I think you mentioned before
the call that you thought was unique to
Cloudflare and something we should talk
about are durable objects. Can you
explain what those are? I'll try my best
because I think whenever even if you
sometimes speak to someone from
Cloudflare, it's one of those things
they struggle to market I think
sometimes cuz it yeah it's tricky but
you can effectively think of a durable
object as it's like a class that you
define in your code. So it looks like a
regular JavaScript class and you write
them you know the methods as you as you
normally would. But what happens is when
you create an instance of this class or
when Cloudflare creates an instance of
this class, we're using the RPC
technology we just talked about. You're
effectively acting on something running
on their web server. So you can think of
it like instantiating a class, but
you're doing it with Cloudflare's SDK
and it gives you a stub and all the
methods that are called will be calling
kind of an instance of that classes
that's on Cloudflare's data centers, but
it's durable. So it comes with built-in
storage. So it has a key value store.
It's not KB. It's own little key value
store. And it also has a SQLized
database in there as well. So it's sort
of like imagine being able to deploy on
demand because you can spin these up in
milliseconds, right? You don't have to
deploy them ahead of time. It's
effective being able to deploy billions
of tiny little mini servers around the
world. And when I say billions, it's
because when I've spoken to some people,
there are literally some customers who
have literally billions of durable
objects. And the nice thing about it is
because Cloudflare's platform is
serverless, even though you have these,
you know, mini servers, you're only
charged when they're running. So if you
make a request, it runs for 2 seconds,
you get charged for that 2 seconds, and
then it will be evicted from memory, and
you don't get charged anymore. And I've
never heard of anything like this
anywhere else. And what they were
initially kind of marketed at is is a
way for multiplayer realtime
communication like you know Google Docs
that kind of stuff because they also
have websockets built in and websockets
are quite complicated but it effectively
implements everything for you that you
need to do for websockets and it has all
these nice little features like storage
websockets and it just it's very unique.
I've never I've never come across
anything quite like it. So it it is hard
to explain but hopefully you got it. So
when you mention it has the websocket
support, are these durable objects
things that the client like the browser
would be able to interact with directly
or is this for interacting from workers?
No. So it's I don't know if you can
actually do it from worker. That's an
interesting one. But it's definitely
definitely mainly used from the client.
So what will happen is you will call a
worker and that worker has a durable
object binding on it. And all that
binding is is you basically tell it the
name of your class. that's defined in
your code. And then when you want to
create a new instance, you just call a
function on that binding and say, "Hey,
give me a new one with this ID." So you
could create, let's take Slack or, you
know, Discord or any of these kind of
chat based applications. Each channel
could effectively be a durable object.
So let's say you're logged into Discord
already because that's not handled by
durable objects or anything, and you
want to join a brand new channel. So you
go through the search through the list,
you find one, you click on it and you
hit join and at that point you need to
be able to receive messages from that
channel, right? And that's all handled
by your durable object. So what will
happen is on the client side it will
make a request and in the browser
there's a library for handling
websockets that just ships with the
browser and you basically give it a URL
and you can pass any parameters you
want. So in this case, it would pass the
channel ID for example, which in Discord
is like a long number. And let's say
we're using that channel ID to
effectively key our durable objects. So
for every single channel that exists in
in the entirety of Discord, there is a
durable object that represents that
channel. And when the client makes a
request to the worker, it basically
says, is the client trying to upgrade to
websockets? And that's basically like a
HTTP header that is just set on the
client automatically when you request a
websocket. If you're creating a brand
new channel, you'll obviously need to
create the dribble object. But let's say
it already exists and you just want to
join an existing channel. You basically
say durable object create me a new one
and pass in that channel ID as its
primary key if you like. And then what
the dur object will do is it will create
a client and server websocket pair
because when you're dealing websockets
there's always a client and a server and
they communicate with each other and
they have a connection. the durable
object will effectively accept the
server side connection. So then it can
receive messages and it will pass the
client websocket back to the client and
then again on the client the client also
accepts the websocket and then when
they're both accepted they're connected
and then let's say okay I've joined the
channel and I want to say hello. So I
type in hello, press enter and
effectively on the client side again
we're just using the browser the browser
APIs that come with websockets and you
just call a method called send websocket
message or something and you can pass
whatever you like in there. So you can
pass a string of hello, but the chances
are you probably want to send a bit more
information like who sent the message
and all that kind of jazz. And then when
they send that message, you've defined a
function on your durable object that's
automatically called by Cloudflare
whenever the client sends a websocket
message to the server. And then your
durable object will be like, "Oh, hey,
I've got a message." It'll wake up. It's
got built-in storage. So let's say all
the storage is kept in that durable
object. So you can create, you know,
SQLite tables to store all the messages.
So you'll probably want to rewrite it to
that storage so that when the next
person joins, right, it can retrieve the
history and send the most recent
messages for people that joined after
initial message sent. And then it can
obviously broadcast it to everyone in
that channel. So let's say there's 100
people in that channel. The durable
object keeps a list of all the clients
that are connected. And you can
basically just retrieve that list of
clients, loop over them, and just
broadcast that message. And that's
fundamentally how it works, at least for
websockets. It sounds a little bit
complicated cuz there's obviously lot of
steps, but like if you invent it in
code, it's really simple and it's really
a really a small amount of code. And
that particular example was with
websockets, but it sounds like you can
interact with them using HTTP calls as
well, just regular ones. Yeah. So I
think durable objects are a way of
representing business entities if you
like in your application. And a really
easy example might be let's say you are
handling support cases. So you know
imagine you you're using as or using any
service out there where you hit a
problem you need to submit support
requests right and the traditional way
to do that will be you might have some
database tables and all that jazz it's
all stored there but with durable
objects each time a new case is created
you can basically create a new durable
object you can you know have the storage
within there and then you can just
define some methods that your worker
calls that interacts with that kind of
entity and it kind of just wraps
everything nicely in a bug
And because you can do things like
websockets, although you don't have to,
you know, like I said, you can just have
this working on regular HTTP, for
example, and just, you know, you press
submit button, it sends a post request,
it calls the worker, so on and the drip
object. I was playing around with
something the other day where a lot of
these tools are email based, right? You
send an email to an email address. A
nice little bit of functionality you can
do with Cloudflare is you can ingest
programmatically email. So you can have
a worker that fires when you receive an
email. So you can imagine you have a
support email, you trigger this worker,
it creates a dribble object and then you
can know you can ping pong messages back
via email. But what I was also able to
do is there was a link in the email that
allowed them to do live chat and they
just press the link and then it has an
ID for the durable object and then you
can switch from email to live chat just
like seamlessly and everything is
encapsulated within this durable object
and you can as I said earlier spin up an
infinite number of these things pretty
much so they scale massively and it kind
of changes a little bit how you think
about building your applications just
cuz it's quite different to have this
kind
functionality if you like. Yeah. So it
it sounds like you have this SQLite
store, this key value store and you can
have all of your clients share these
objects. Any client who needs to have
access to the same information like the
example you gave was like a Discord chat
channel. Everybody in the channel would
want to see the messages that other
people are sending so they would all be
interacting with the same durable
object. I think what some people might
be wondering is earlier we were talking
about D1 which is the SQLite offering
and KV which is the key value store.
What's the distinction for people who
want to store data and share data
between using those services and and
using durable objects? I think my
opinion on it would be that the durable
objects you can probably imagine they're
a little bit tricky to grasp. So I think
Katie was there because it was the very
first thing that they built to work with
workers. It's definitely still heavily
used for like those hybrid cases. But I
think if I was going to start a brand
new project and I was going to reach for
something that I wanted to like store my
data and like I said, you know, with D1
at the moment, you need to split by 10
and it's a bit difficult to do. But with
durable objects, like I said, you could
spin those up on demand and I think they
actually have higher storage. I think
you can store 50 gig in a durable object
which obviously if you're thinking about
a list of chat messages that's that's a
lot of chat messages and obviously you
know you can have things in place where
it archives off data and stuff right if
you think about Discord how often do you
need messages from like 6 years ago
probably very infrequently right I think
D1 is there I wouldn't be surprised it's
there to make people feel comfortable
because when you think about imagine if
you didn't have a database like you went
to you know Cloudflare and there's no
database you'd be like, "Huh, they've
got everything, but where's the
database?" And if you didn't twig, they
have this powerful durable object. You
might just kind of discount it as not
having the thing. So, I think it's a
tricky thing cuz then they're also
relying on education and teaching people
about durable objects and how they work
cuz they are very different. What I
would say though is for some data, D1's
always going to be better. I think
particularly when it has read replicas
because of the nature of them durable
objects when they're created they exist
in that place. So if a request comes
into your worker in Europe that durable
object will also live in Europe
indefinitely. So even if we were
communicating via a durable object it
would either be in Europe or it be in
the US. And with D1 once they have read
replicas right you're going to have
lower latency. So yeah, if you have
stuff that's, you know, you're not going
to breach the limit of D1, I would
definitely reach for D1, particularly
when they have read replicas, but if you
do need that global coordination, and
there is a lot of stuff that needs that
global coordination, right? Like you
think we're talking multiplayer and
Discord, but Google Docs for example,
right? You can see where people's or
like Miro, all these tools, you can see
where people's mice are in real time,
where they're clicking, the typing in
real time, right? There's so much
realtime stuff that's really tricky to
coordinate. That's why there's only one
durable object or one instance of that
durable object at any one time is to
enable this kind of global kind of
communication. And has it been stated by
cloud player themselves that there will
never be the equivalent of a read
replica? This will be a single instance
for durable objects for durable. Yeah, I
think it's by design. So I've never seen
anything about read replicas because I
think it's one of those things where
it's there to enable global
synchronization across many clients and
it's also designed to remove some of the
problems you have with that. So it's
it's single threaded for example. So if
you have multiple requests come into it
they will be cued but then that removes
the problem of things like transactions
and you know multiple rights happening
in different places and all that kind of
stuff. So there are benefits to them and
they do have even though it's single
threaded they can go up to a thousand
requests a second. So they're by no
means small they're smaller than mighty
I guess I would say in nature. Yeah. I
mean that also may help people make a
decision in terms of when they make
sense because I'm assuming if you're
single threaded even if you have a read
heavy workload at some point you're
going to hit the ceiling depending on
how your application is designed. Yes.
But I think because they're designed to
be split in whichever way is sensible, I
think you'd have to get to like enormous
enormous scale before you hit that
problem. Like you can imagine even the
most busiest of Discord servers, right?
They're not that busy. I don't think
I've ever been in a Discord where it's a
thousand messages sent per second. I'm
sure maybe there are I'm sure maybe are
some some crazy ones during like
sporting events maybe where there are
super high messages, but a thousand
requests a second is is a lot, right?
Even if I watch like a live YouTube
video, right, and you have the live chat
on the right, and it's like flying
through messages, it's still nowhere
close to that, right? Maybe at like
unbelievable scale, you might hit that
limit. But I think it's definitely one
of those things where up front you need
to decide a good partition. You can't
just have one durable object for your
entire application, right? You need to
split it by user or channel or, you
know, some kind of sensible thing and
then I think you'll be fine for a very
very long time. Yeah. I mean, if you
take an example of say a corporate Slack
server, then I could see maybe the
entire business as a whole, maybe
there's a thousand messages going
through a second. But then if you scope
it down to per channel, for example,
then it would be much less. So I I
suppose that's all a part of your design
and like you mentioned, how you
partition or how you choose when to
create durable objects. Yeah, exactly.
It's similar to even if you weren't
using durable objects, right? It's how
you partition your data and that's one
of the most important decisions you can
make up front is how you create your
database tables, how they link together,
and all that kind of stuff. So, yeah,
it's kind of good engineering still
applies. Tying all these things
together, can you give an example of a a
project you've worked on with Cloudflare
and how all those services connect and
and what you used? I have a few. I think
one of the ones I've been working on at
the moment is you know AI is all the
rage and I was building effectively
what's like a rag pipeline. So you can
imagine you're building something with
AI and you need to do some rag which for
anyone not familiar effectively is like
retrieving like relevant context before
you prompt the LM and you're passing it
some relevant context and to do that you
kind of pass the let's say the user's
query that they've typed into let's just
say a chatbot and you want to retrieve
all the relevant sources that you've
stored somewhere right that you've built
over time and then you want to pass that
so it has more contextual information to
help answer the query. And on the face
of it, it sounds quite simple. You know,
you have some data and you just need to
retrieve it. There's actually quite a
lot of moving pieces. And I think I
found that the ones on the market, there
was some like good ones, but I think
it's one of those spaces where there's a
lot of room for people to kind of go in
and do it. So, I thought I just want to
try building them. And in terms of what
you need, you need to be able to create
kind of logical databases if you like,
like knowledge bases. And effectively,
each one for me was a durable object.
Users can upload files. So let's say
this is basically the information that
you're giving like the knowledge you're
giving to the AI and those can be in
like markdown, CSV, PDF, all sorts of
formats. So you need to have something
that handles all of those. But you can
just store that on R2, the equivalent of
S3. And then Cloudflare, we've talked
about the main products, but they have a
vector database called Vectorize, which
does exactly what it says on the tin.
You basically give it an embedding which
is like a mathematical representation of
your data and you give it to a ve
database and then you can query it and
say give me all the similar kind of
pieces of text based on the input query
and then I tie all these things together
with a workflow because I need to
retrieve each individual document. You
need to be able to kind of separate it
cuz the document could be hundreds of
pages long and obviously you don't want
to insert 100 pages in one go. you might
want to separate it into like 200
character chunks or a thousand chunks or
or whatever. Then you need to generate
those embeddings that I was talking
about using a body model. And somewhat
surprisingly, we haven't talked about AI
at all, but Cloudflare does have an AI
product called Workers AI where they run
their inference globally. So in all the
places your your work can run, I'm
pretty sure that they also have GPUs
that run a number of like open-source
models. They don't have any of the big
ones like Anthropic, Open AR, or
anything like that, but they do have the
the Llama models. they have a deep seed
model and and stuff like that and some
of the open source embedding model as
well. So I use that as well. And then
once you've generated the embeddings,
you need to insert them into the vector
database. And then after that, because
you've chunk the document, you then need
to store each chunk somewhere. Each
chunk is goes into the geopolitic
effectively and all these things tied
together. So it's probably the project I
use that uses the most amount of
Cloudflare services. The other one
that's a lot simpler and maybe a bit
easier to grasp because there's lots of
moving parts in that one is I'm quite
into like my esports, so like
competitive gaming. And me and my
friends, we all play League of Legends
for anyone that plays. And we also like
watch esports. And we were kind of
wanted the schedule of the games and we
also wanted to know when the games were
happening live. Sometimes we'd forget.
So I built a Discord bot where it
scrapes the content off the official
website. It pulls out in the schedule
and it also takes like screenshots of
the standings that you can get. And most
importantly, it runs the work on a
5minute schedule. So you could you have
crrons that you're available like you're
used to and it just spins up the work
every five minutes and it basically
checks if there's a live game and if it
is it posts like a thread on discord and
says hey there's a game happening like
and then people just jump on and chat
about the game. So that uses a few
different ones like I said like uses
worker uses D1 the scraping like we
haven't talked about it but they have a
product that's basically like puppeteer
as a service called browser rendering
where you can basically you know browse
websites programmatically and scrape and
screenshots and stuff. So yeah, those
are probably a couple. You mentioned the
languages you can use and you've
mentioned the different services they
have. In your experience, when you write
like let's say your JavaScript or your
TypeScript code, is the majority of it
agnostic to the platform? I mean,
outside of the interactions with the
specific services, do you feel like you
have to write code that's specifically
for Cloudflare, or is it more that
there's still large parts of your code
that if you needed to move to another
platform, you feel like you could? I
think by and large the vast majority of
the code you write will just be like
vanilla TypeScript or vanilla JavaScript
or obviously you might use packages
right from npm or wherever you want to
get them from but because at its core
it's the same runtime that runs in your
browser or in some cases like I said
CloudFare has ported node compatibility
but obviously node is a very well-known
runtime it's almost like a smaller
runtime than let's say node for example
if you want to take this and run it
somewhere let's say lambda that is full
node it's much easier than doing the
reverse right so I think that's also one
of the challenges of if you do run a
full node environment you can move it to
cloudflare and you can be like oh this
library isn't available so it doesn't
work right which happens a lot less now
cuz like I said they've expanded the
compatibility but it's a lot safer I
guess to go from something that's more
kind of niche or condensed and that
makes it easier to move it elsewhere
there obviously there are things like
the bindings right Those are entirely
proprietary to Cloudflare. So those
would cause you a problem. I think if it
were me and like if I were building
something that would stand the test of
time. I'm still I'm going to write it in
a way where let's take the ports and
adapters like architecture pattern,
right? Where you basically encapsulate
anything that's external to your
application is encapsulated in an
adapter. So let's say you're talking to
D1 or KV or whatever it might be. I
would wrap it in a class and then all
communication goes via that single class
and that way let's say I want to move
right I'm not happy for whatever reason
all I have to do is change the code in
that adapter and because I'm returning
objects that are agnostic of Cloudflare
of course you have the data right you
have to move the data that bit's going
to be the tricky bit but the actual code
as long as you're doing it in a way that
is you know there's good engineering
practice in there I think you can limit
the blast radius of the impact if you
had to move And like I said, the core of
it will absolutely be movable because
it's like writing JavaScript in your in
your browser. As we wrap up, if somebody
wants to get started with Cloudflare,
you have a book. How do you recommend
they get started? So, if you want to get
started, obviously my book will be a
great introduction. So, you can get that
directly from the Pragmatic bookshelf.
That's an ebook and it's also available
from Amazon and all the kind of big book
retailers out there. I think it covers
everything we've talked about. So, all
the services we talked about, workers
and everything like that. The docs on
Cloud's website are pretty good. They've
just rewritten a lot of them. So, if you
don't want to buy the book, then
absolutely read the docs. There are a
ton of tutorials on there that are great
to get started. Lots of code. Cloud
themselves have a YouTube channel.
They're slowly adding more things on. I
think if you want to see, I think it's
one of their Devril people go through. I
think it's like an hourong video of like
an workers 101 I think it's called. And
that's a really good primer on getting
started with Cloudflare. And outside of
that, like I mentioned, if you're the
kind of person that just wants to learn
by hacking and slashing something away,
you can go and sign up for a free
account right now. You'll get access to
everything I talked about apart from
durable objects. And there might be one
or one or two more that are exclusively
on the paid plan. But yeah, you can spin
up a worker, you know, use D1, use
workflows, you know, whatever it might
be today, and then just yeah, get
learning yourself. And also if you do
get stuck like I said you can reach out
to me or there's also the discord which
is there's like I don't know 70,000
engineers are on that on that discord
and everyone's really helpful. It's like
a really nice community where people
post you know I'm stuck with this and
people will reply and talk to you talk
about things. So that's also a good way
to get into the community I think. And
if people want to reach out to you how
do they find you? If you want to reach
out to me, you can find me. I think East
one is probably on X and I'm Ashley.
Ashley, thanks so much for chatting with
me about building apps on Cloudflare.
Yeah, thank you. It's been fun. I really
enjoyed our conversation. So, thank you.
This has been Jeremy Jung for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net. net to
provide feedback. You can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
[Music]
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at
teamseradio.net. This and all other
episodes of SE Radio is licensed under
Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for
listening.